Guide to the Montana Women's Bureau records 1973-1981
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Montana Women's Bureau records
1973-1981
Montana Historical Society Archives
RS 386
Montana. Women's Bureau.
1 linear feet of shelf space
The Montana Women's Bureau was formed under the Department of Labor's Employment Relations Division. These records (1973-1981) consist of correspondence, press releases, publications, reports, subject files, and clippings.
In an effort to "enable women to reach their fullest potential of service and contribution to society" the 43rd Montana Legislature, passed legislation requiring the Department of Labor to study the difficulties women faced in the work place and serve as a watch dog on public and private employment practices. To oversee and coordinate this effort, the Montana Women's Bureau was created within the Employment Relations Division in 1974. In addition the Montana Advisory Council on Women was created.
The first Bureau Chief was Sue Bartlett, who served in that post until replaced by Joan Duncan in 1975. Joan Duncan remained in that position until 1981. The Women's Bureau served as a clearing house for access to information regarding grants, discrimination, occupational education and training, sexual harassment, child and health care, and other issues of special interest to female employees. The Bureau published a newsletter, provided job hunting information, produced weekly television news spot, sponsored seminars, conducted surveys, and served as a resource library.
The Bureau lost its funding during the 1981 Legislature after extensive debate over funding shortfalls and possible duplication of services within the Department of Labor.
These records of the Montana Women's Bureau consist of general and interoffice correspondence (1973-1981); news releases (1974-1980); copies of Newsbriefs (1980-1981) the Bureau newsletter; monthly reports (1977-1981); project reports (1978); subject files (1978-1981); miscellany (1981) including mailing and referral lists; and clippings (1974-1981).
The collection is arranged by series.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Women employees--Montana.; Sex discrimination against women--Montana.
Montana; Women
Detailed Description of the Collection
- General Correspondence
  - A-W (filed chronologically within each letter of the alphabet), 1978-1981 (Box-folder 1 / 1-23)
- Interoffice Correspondence
  - Department of Labor and Industry Commissioners Office (primarily with Commissioner David E. Fuller), 1978-1980 (Box-folder 1 / 24)
  - Department of Labor and Industry Labor Standards Division (primarily with Division Administrator, Dick Kane), 1978-1981 (Box-folder 1 / 25)
- Press Releases
  - Press releases (re various women's issues), 1974-1980 (Box-folder 1 / 26)
- Printed Materials
  - Newsbriefs (newsletter of the Women's Bureau), 1979-1981 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
- Reports
  - "A Report on the Montana Job Service" (re results of Job Service Survey on Women), 1978 December (Box-folder 2 / 2)
  - Monthly reports, 1977-1981 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
- Subject Files
  - Job Service survey, 1978 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
  - Job Service training programs for women, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
  - Legislation: abolishing the Women's Bureau, 1981 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
  - Legislation: establishing Women's Bureau (includes legislative charge from the Montana Codes.), 1973-1974 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
  - "News from the Women's Bureau" (materials relating to newspaper column of this title), 1980-1981 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
  - Program priorities, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
  - "Survey of Women and Work", 1978 August-September (Box-folder 2 / 10)
  - Women's Bureau survey, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
  - Women's Bureaus: National Department of Labor, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 2 / 12)
  - Women's Bureaus: Regional--Denver Regional Office, 1981 (Box-folder 2 / 13)
  - Women's Bureaus: State (not Montana), 1978-1979 (Box-folder 2 / 14)
  - Women's Bureaus: U.S. Women's Bureau, 1978-1981 (Box-folder 2 / 15)
- Miscellany
  - Bibliography on sexual harassment, 1981 June (Box-folder 2 / 16)
  - Mailing list, 1981 June 19 (Box-folder 2 / 17)
  - Referral list, 1981 (Box-folder 2 / 18)
- Clippings
  - Newspaper clippings (re Montana Women's Bureau and various programs and events relating to women's issues), 1974-1981 (Box-folder 2 / 19)